[Bow!]
拜
[In the 5th year of the Yuanhe era,]
大苍元和五年
[Emperor Xiao Huan and the Crown Prince]
文宗萧桓
[both passed away.]
与太子先后病逝
[While still an infant,]
尚在襁褓中的
[Crown Prince Xiao Qi ascended the throne]
皇太孙萧麒即位
[and changed the era name to Shengli.]
改年号为圣历
[The Queen, long aiding governance,]
辅政已久的皇后周姁
[was later honored as the Empress Dowager.]
被尊为太皇太后
[She wields absolute power]
垂帘听政
[behind the scenes.]
独掌大权
Long live the emperor!
吾皇万岁万岁万万岁
My lord,
报告大阁领
I conducted interrogations all night.
审了一晚上
The suspects confessed to their crimes,
嫌犯皆已招认罪行
but refuse to identify the mastermind.
但不肯交代幕后主使
The...
白
The White Death!
白无常
I...
我
I'll tell you everything...
我说
[I was merely assisting the trafficking.]
我只是帮他们运人而已
[There's a buyer in Jian Nan,]
剑南那边有个买家
who wants to acquire 100 kids as slaves.
要收一百个孩童为奴
Take them away.
带下去
Next time,
下次
don't wait for me to intervene.
别再等我亲自出手
Understood.
是
[Let's go to the palace.]
进宫
I have heard that mother was
儿臣听闻母后
mourning the passing of the Royal Advisor,
哀国师之仙逝
and you're indisposed,
凤体欠安
so I  was copying scriptures until dawn
故抄经到天明
to pray for mother's recovery.
祈求母后康复
You show such filial devotion,
贤王有此孝心
which brings great comfort to me.
哀家心甚慰啊
Thanks to you, Lord Zhang.
这也是张相你这个老师
You have taught him exceptionally well.
教得好啊
I cannot take any credit for that.
臣不敢当
It is truly the virtue of His Highness.
那是贤王殿下
[Filial, respectful and loyal.]
孝悌忠信
[He is kind-hearted and benevolent.]
宅心仁厚
[It is simply his nature.]
天性使然
Lord Shen didn't attend the assembly, huh?
沈卿今天没来上朝
Lord Shen's been occupied with his duties.
沈大阁领公务繁忙
He's known for his remarkable feats.
屡立奇功
Perhaps he simply
大概
has no time to attend the assembly.
是无暇上朝吧
[The Imperial Guard's (IG) head, Shen Du, arrives!]
内卫府阁领沈渡到
Greetings, Your Highness.
太皇太后
No formalities, Lord Shen.
沈卿请起
Your Highness,
启禀太皇太后
I was just at the headquarters,
臣刚在内卫府
busy with the investigation of
忙着审理
the case involving 100 missing children.
百名孩童失踪案
The suspects have all confessed.
嫌犯皆已招供
That's why I came in late.
来迟一步
Please forgive me, Your Highness.
请太皇太后恕罪
This case has caused great anxiety
此案闹得
among the people of Xiang'an City.
襄安城人心惶惶
I entrusted this case to you,
把此案交给你办
and it seems I did the right thing.
果然没错
Lord Shen,
沈卿啊
it's quite a coincidence.
说来也巧了
Early this morning,
张相一大早
Lord Zhang came to me
提前替你向哀家
to request a reward for you.
讨赏了
Lord Shen has consistently
这沈大阁领
turned the tide in difficult situations.
每每力挽狂澜
Truly, he is a paragon among us.
实乃吾辈之楷模呀
Gratitude, Lord Zhang.
多谢张相记挂
I was simply doing my job.
内卫职责所在
I desire no reward.
沈渡无需奖赏
Lord Zhang and the Imperial Guard
张相同内卫府
have always been at odds with each other.
向来势同水火
Now, this is
如今这是
turning hostility into goodwill, huh?
化干戈为玉帛了
Yongan.
永安
My apologies.
儿臣知错
My officials are so harmonious and united.
文武官员如此和睦齐心
This is a blessing for the royal family.
这是哀家之幸啊
Lord Shen,
沈卿啊
today I wish to
哀家今日
grant you a marriage.
要赐你一门婚事
What do you think?
如何
[White Death always acts on his own terms.]
那白无常向来我行我素
[Sir, how do you know]
老师是如何知道
[that he will agree]
今日他会答应
[to this marriage today?]
这门婚事的
[Shen Du is known as the White Death.]
沈渡号称白无常
[His cruelty is merely toward the enemy.]
凶残杀戮那是对外
To the Empress Dowager
面对太皇太后
he is simply a
他不过是一个
courtier eager to gain favor.
一心想往上爬的宠臣
Does he fear that resisting the marriage
他担心抗拒赐婚
will lead to losing
会失去
the Empress Dowager's trust?
太皇太后的信任吗
[Even if you are a ghost of misfortune,]
就算你是无常恶鬼
[you still have your own desires.]
也会有私欲啊
Xing!
六娘 六娘 六娘
- Good morning, Xing! - Good morning.
六娘早 六娘 早
- Xing! - Morning!
六娘 早
- Morning, Xing. - Xing!
早啊六娘 六娘
Good morning!
早
Clerk Yan, morning.
颜书吏 这么早
[Watch out!]
小心
[Those are the petals I just dried.]
我刚晒的花瓣
[Watch out.]
小心啊
[I'm sorry, clerk Yan.]
对不起啊 颜书吏
It's all right, it's all right.
没事没事
- Good morning, Yan Xing. - Morning.
早啊 颜幸 早
- Morning, Xing.
早  早啊 六娘
[You didn't have breakfast,]
大早上起来
[did you?]
你就没吃饭是不是
I've had enough of this.
真服了你了
See?
看见了没
[Women are useless]
这女子在刑部
[in the Ministry of Justice!]
能干什么呀
[If Lady Xu, the Chief Royal Steward who's]
被太皇太后身边的
[close to the Empress Dowager heard it,]
徐内司听见了
[she'll blame you for hindering her plans]
要怪您阻了她
[to allow women to serve as officials.]
女子入仕大计
Aren't you extremely talkative today?
你今儿怎么那么多话呀
You've done your work or something?
没事干是吧
Get back to work!
干活去
Attend to the archives!
归档
My lord.
大人
Yan Xing!
颜幸
Tea!
茶
My lord.
大人
Today,
今天啊
from the inspector,
异良人那边呢
a case has come in
送了个
regarding a woman
雁归山的案子过来
[from Yan Gui Mountain.]
说是有一户家的娘子
[It is said that she encountered a ghost]
撞了鬼
[and hanged herself.]
上吊自杀了
[My lord, you've got to know that]
大人 我跟您说啊
I've been
这我手下
overwhelmed with
这些细碎的案子
these trivial cases.
一堆一堆的
Me and my subordinates
我跟我手下的那些兄弟
can't even find time to sleep,
别说睡觉了
let alone
我连吃饭的时间
have our meals.
我都没有
I'm requesting from the higher authorities
我呢也在向上面申请
to increase our manpower.
得加派人手啊
[Yeah.]
对
[Two years ago,]
两年前
it took us some effort to recruit a clerk,
好不容易招一杂吏
and it turned out to be
还是
a woman.
女的
As for this case,
这个呢
we'll wait for the inspector
等异良人那边
to complete his investigation.
查完报过来
Then we can file it...
直接录了归档
To avoid future complications.
不要节外生枝
Yes, my lord.
是
[Yan Gui Mountain?]
雁归山
[Suicide?]
自杀
You Xiang'an folks disregard propriety.
你们襄安城还真不讲究
In my place, the death of a county official
我们那地儿
means no one dares to hang festive silks.
死个县令也不敢扎彩绸
The Royal Advisor has passed away
这国师死了
for barely a month, right?
也就一个月吧
This place is all decorated,
这张灯结彩的
without any sense of taboo.
也没个忌讳
What do you know?
你懂什么
The Royal Advisor was
国师那可是
a saint who understood the will of God.
知天命的大神
He even...
就连
He even prophesied the
就连当今太皇太后主政
Empress Dowager's governance.
都是他预言的
Really?
是吗
It'll surely be a scene for his funeral!
国师走那地儿都神了
All officials must pay respects today.
今天官员都要去祭拜
The Dark Demon is coming!
黑罗刹来了 黑罗刹来了
Go inside!
快走
Hide yourself, now!
快躲起来
Who is this?
这什么人
How come everyone is acting
怎么大家伙
like they are seeing a ghost?
都跟见了鬼一样
You don't know him?
黑罗刹你都不知道
He established the Imperial Inspectorate (II),
御察司就是他建的
specializing in surveillance and torture.
专职告密酷刑
I've heard they possess hundreds
听说里面的刑具
of torture devices.
有上百件
Anyone who enters
但凡入院
never escapes unscathed.
未有不从
If anyone resists,
但有不从
they would wish for a quick death!
求生无能 求死无门啊
[White Death is coming!]
白无常来了
[White Death is also heading this way!]
白无常也来了
So this is the "White Death?"
这就是白无常啊
White Death is
白无常
Commander Shen of the Imperial Guard.
就是内卫府的沈大阁领
The Imperial Guard is quite powerful.
这内卫府可了不得
It's directly under the Empress Dowager.
直隶太皇太后
They handle investigations, surveillance,
侦查 监视 刺杀
and assassinations.
什么都干
[Stop crying!]
别哭了
[The White Death is here.]
白无常来了
Just hearing his name,
闻其名
the clouds disperse in broad daylight,
白日云散
and it stops kids from crying at night!
夜止小儿哭啊
Now their convoys
这两个人的车队
have run into each other.
撞在一起
There's going to be a good show.
可有好戏看了
The street isn't very wide.
道就这么宽
Who will yield first?
谁会先让
Who knows?
那谁知道
Let's watch!
看看看 看
Stop!
停车
Commander Shen is coming after all.
沈大阁领还是来了
I thought
我原以为
you would be too busy
你忙着准备婚事
preparing for your wedding.
来不了了呢
My wedding is nothing
沈某的婚事
compared to state affairs.
怎比得上国家大事
Lord Zhang made the request,
张相提请
and Her Highness graciously approved it.
太皇太后恩准
This indicates that Commander Shen's
足见沈大阁领的婚事
marriage is indeed significant.
亦是大事
It's a pity, though,
只可惜啊
that the previous brides
前几位新娘子
lacked a bit of fortune.
少了点福分
Very funny, Chancellor Lai.
来中丞说笑了
To avoid missing the auspicious time,
为免误了祈福吉时
we should set off now.
还是速速上路吧
This street is just too narrow.
这西街还是太窄
It could hardly accommodate
竟容不得
the passage of our people.
区区两路人马通行
Clear the way on both sides.
把这两旁挡路的
Get them removed!
都给我拆了
So both II and IG
御察司和内卫府
could get through.
可并肩而行
Commander, please!
大阁领
Let's go!
走
[Shen Du?]
沈渡
I've been waiting for you two.
两位让老夫好等啊
Greetings, Lord Zhang.
张相
I apologize for being late.
晚辈来迟了
But it seems you arrived just in time.
倒未来迟
It's the auspicious moment now.
恰逢吉时
Everyone,
诸位
let's start the ceremony.
开始祭拜吧
[The auspicious moment is upon us!]
吉时到
Gratitude, Clerk Yan,
多谢颜书吏
if it weren't for you, we wouldn't
若不是你来
have uncovered the true culprit.
定不能查明真凶
You're welcome.
客气
Conducting verifications for murder cases
核准命案
is the duty of the Ministry of Justice.
本就是刑部分内的事情
Speaking of which,
对了
a few days ago,
前几日
you asked us to assist in investigating
你让我们帮忙调查
the herbs that can detect poison.
能够验毒的草药
I have received some info.
如今我已经探查到了
There are some on a nearby mountain.
附近的山上便有
Why not accompany our carriage
要不你随我们的车马
and go up the mountain to collect them?
一同上山去采
There's no need to trouble yourselves.
不用麻烦了
You should return and report back.
你们快回去复命吧
I can handle it myself.
我自己上山采了便是
If that's the case,
既如此
then I'll take my leave.
那便告辞
So long.
告辞
Today's prayer was successfully conducted,
今日祈福
thanks to Lord Zhang's oversight,
多亏张相主持大局
so we could proceed smoothly.
才能顺利进行
In the coming year,
我大苍来年
our Great nation will surely
定会如国师预言般
realize the Royal Advisor's prophecy,
凤引九雏
bringing peace to the realm.
天下太平啊
The officials' prayers for blessings are
此次百官祈福
attributed to His Highness, Prince Xian,
那是贤王殿下
who has visited some remarkable figures
探访民间的神人
and chosen this auspicious day
特定下此良辰吉日
to allay Her Highness' concerns.
为太皇太后排忧解难
I was merely following orders,
老夫只是听令行事
fulfilling my duties as a loyal subject.
尽了臣子的本分
[Our Great Cang,]
我大苍啊
[with a wise ruler and virtuous officials,]
君圣臣贤
[we are fortunate to live in]
臣等生逢此
[such an era of]
海晏河清之盛世
[peace and prosperity!]
真乃人生一大幸事啊
[Indeed.]
是啊
[Assassin!]
有刺客
[Secure the mountain perimeter.]
封山
Lady, are you gathering
姐姐
these leaves for medicinal purposes?
你是要采这树叶做草药
No.
不是
I'm using them for autopsy...
我是用来验尸
That's right.
对
I am using them for medicinal purposes.
我就是用来做草药的
How did you know?
你怎么知道的
Just looking at your outfit gives it away.
看姐姐这打扮就知道了
You're a healer, aren't you?
你是医官
I suppose you could say that.
也算是吧
Here, take this.
这个给你
I've gathered enough already.
我采够了
Aunt Zhang from my village fell sick,
村口的张大娘犯了病
so I came to gather some for her.
我来帮她采几枝
Last time, the healer mentioned
上回也是大夫说
that soaking this in water is beneficial.
这个泡了喝有用
Let me pay you.
那我买下来
No need for payment!
不要钱 不要钱
I just randomly picked it up.
我也是随手采的
Thank you very much!
那谢谢你了
Lady,
姐姐
my name is Qi Yeyun.
我叫齐野云
What's your name?
姐姐叫什么
Are you heading down the mountain?
姐姐是要下山吗
I can show you a shortcut.
我带你走小道吧
I will be faster.
下山快
Halt!
站住 站住
Today,
今日
no one is allowed to go down the mountain.
谁也不许下山
What's going on?
发生什么事了
I'm a clerk from the Ministry of Justice.
我是刑部书吏
Stop talking.
休要多话
Come with us.
和我们走
Hurry, let's go!
快走 走
What's happening here?
干什么呀这是
Chancellor Lai,
来中丞
everyone from the mountain
事发之时
has been brought here.
山中之人已全部带到
On the day of the prayer for blessings,
明堂祈福之日
how could anyone
居然有人
dare to assassinate a court official?
胆敢刺杀朝廷命官
[I narrowly escaped an arrow.]
本官命大逃过一箭
[But I have lost my beloved subordinate.]
可本官却痛失爱将
Today,
今日
I'll definitely have my revenge.
本官定要血刃刺客
Assassin?
刺客
Who might that be?
不知道谁是刺客呀
He is in your midst.
刺客就在你们当中
I advise the assassin
本官奉劝刺客
to confess now.
现在就认罪
I can ensure you
我可以让他
a more merciful death.
死得舒服一点
If you refuse to confess,
不敢认罪
you will still not escape.
一样逃不过
Within one incense's time,
一炷香内
if no one confesses,
若无人认罪
there will be no mercy.
格杀勿论
Wait!
慢着
Chancellor Lai,
来中丞
I'm clerk Yan Xing from the Ministry of Justice.
我是刑部书吏颜幸
I beg your permission to examine the corpse.
可否让我看一看尸体
Perhaps I can determine
或许我能查出
who the assassin is.
刺客是谁
Granted!
可
[It's now the hour of the rooster (5pm.)]
现在是酉时
[The sun is setting in the west.]
太阳位于西边
[So the shooting position...]
所以射杀位置
What do you think, Ms. clerk?
怎么样啊 小书吏
Can you tell me
你可以告诉我
who the assassin is now?
刺客是谁了
I have not yet identified
我还未查出
who the assassin is.
刺客是谁
However,
但是
the assassin used a long-range shot.
刺客属于远距离射杀
The bright sunlight
艳阳直射
would have affected his aim.
会影响他的瞄准
Therefore, he must have been on
所以他一定处于
the shady side during the assassination.
刺杀时辰的阴面
Considering the direction
综合箭支射入的
from which the arrow struck,
方向来看
the best hiding spot
最佳潜伏点
would be in a tree.
就是在树上
Located on the northwest peak,
位于西北山峰
in the high forest.
高处的山林里
After the incident, the II
案发后
immediately sealed off the mountain,
御察司迅速封山
so the people from other mountains
故其他山脉中的民众
could not possibly be the assassin.
必然不可能是刺客
Chancellor Lai,
来中丞
I urge you
我恳请
to release the
把没有嫌疑的百姓
innocent civilians.
先给放了
I have already
我已经把话
made myself clear.
说得很清楚了
The condition for their release
放人的条件是
is to find out who the assassin is.
查出刺客是谁
You have not achieved that.
你没办到
Execute them all.
全部射杀
Chancellor Lai,
来中丞
I have a more amusing idea.
沈某有个更有趣的法子
Simply killing the assassin
仅是射杀刺客
is too unremarkable.
未免也太不震慑人了
I have raised a few fighting hounds,
沈某养了几只斗犬
and their ability to tear apart criminals
撕咬罪犯的能力
is quite impressive.
甚是出众
Why not let my dogs
不如让我的犬
come out and have a feast?
出来试试嘴
Although the killing will be a bit slow,
虽然杀人的速度慢了点
it will be
但
quite entertaining.
很有趣啊
I truly feel that
来某真是白担了
my nickname "Dark Demon"
黑罗刹之名
pales in comparison to
与沈大阁领一比
Commander Shen.
自愧不如
I'm truly humbled.
甘拜下风
Jinglin.
景林
Don't come any closer!
别过来 别过来
Stop!
停
Stay away from me!
别过来
Get away!
走开
No, no!
别过来 别过来
The assassin is among these people.
刺客就在这几人之中
The assassin must be someone
刺客必然是
with considerable strength and speed
力量和速度都很强的人
and capable of climbing.
且会攀爬
Chancellor Lai,
来中丞
you can deal with
这几个人
these individuals now.
你可以好好整治一番了
Let me think,
让我想想
what kind of punishment
哪种死法
would be most fitting for them.
更适合他们
I implore you, Lord Lai,
恳请来中丞
to wait a bit before taking action.
等些时辰再做处置
Just give me a bit more time,
只要再给我一点时间
and I will surely identify
我必定会抓到
the true assassin.
唯一的凶手
I swear on my life.
我愿以性命为担保
Commander Shen,
沈大阁领
how much time do you think
你觉得
I should give her?
几个时辰比较适合呢
Six hours.
三个时辰
After six hours,
三个时辰后
if you still cannot uncover the truth,
若你查不出来
then you can join them in death.
便同他们一起去死吧
[For those who wield bows and arrows,]
用弓箭之人
[there'll be calluses in three spots on hands.]
手会有三个部位生茧
[This one only has calluses on his palm,]
此人只有掌心有茧
[so he's innocent.]
排除
My lord,
大阁领
Lai Luozhi wants to identify the assassin.
这来罗织自己要找刺客
Yet he handed over the suspects and
却把人和案子
the investigation to the Imperial Guard.
都扔给我们内卫府
Claiming that he wants
说什么
our dogs to carry out the execution.
想让我们斗犬来行刑
Do you think
你说
there might be some trickery at play?
这当中会不会有诈
What trickery could there be?
能有什么诈呀
It's simply that he is confident
无非就是笃定
the clerk won't be able to figure it out.
那个小书吏查不出来
He won't kill anyone from the Ministry of Justice.
他也不想杀刑部的人
That will get himself into trouble.
惹一身腥臊
If he's trying to avoid trouble,
那他不想惹一身腥臊
are you not concerned
您就不怕
about causing a scandal?
惹出是非口舌吗
I've been a son of a criminal before,
罪臣之子都当过了
so what's there to fear?
还怕惹什么腥臊啊
[The assassin's position was]
刺客的方位
[at the high point of the northwest peak,]
为西北山峰高处
[and the forest there]
而那处种植的山林
[is a lacquer tree forest.]
为漆树林
[If someone touches lacquer trees,]
有人碰触漆树树枝
[they will develop rashes.]
便起了满身斑疹
[And when the guards]
而侍卫白天
[apprehended the suspects during the day,]
抓到嫌疑人时
[none of them exhibited any rashes.]
无一人身上有斑疹
[Those with severe rashes]
起斑严重的人
[can be ruled out as]
可排除
[potential suspects hiding in the forest.]
潜伏于漆树林的可能
[This man in the middle,]
中间这个人
[the dirt on his shoes]
鞋上的泥土
[is not from the lacquer tree forest.]
并非漆树林的泥土
[Thus, he can be ruled out.]
排除
If we can locate the murder weapon,
找到凶器
we will identify the killer.
就能知道凶手是谁了
[Why is it so bright here?]
怎么这么亮
Do you have any last words?
可有遗言想要留下
Six hours are almost up.
三个时辰就要到了
You haven't discovered who the killer is.
你还未查出刺客是谁
Wait for the guards
等内卫
to find the murder weapon in the forest
在漆树林找到凶器
and compare it,
加以比对
- then - You don't need to explain anything to me.
就 你不用跟我解释
You're running out of time.
你已经没有时间再等
Finding the murder weapon
找到凶器
doesn't guarantee you'll identify him,
你也没有十足的把握
right?
不是吗
Does a lack of complete confidence
没有十足的把握
stop you from taking action?
便不去做吗
To gamble your life
无十足的把握
without full confidence
却以性命作赌
is either incredibly foolish
要么是愚蠢至极
or shows a lack of self-respect.
要么就是自轻自贱
When the time comes, I'll leave a letter,
到时候我会留下一封遗书
please ensure it is delivered to Erudite
劳烦送到
Yan's residence in the east of the city.
城东颜博士府
Take clerk Yan away,
带颜书吏下去
and see her off properly.
好好地送她一程
Yes, my lord.
是
Commander Shen!
沈大阁领
Do you truly not recognize me?
你真的不认识我了吗
Do I have to recognize you?
我需要认识你吗
[My lord,]
大阁领
[the murder weapon has been uncovered.]
凶器找到了
[Just as clerk Yan suspected,]
如颜书吏所猜测的那样
[it was buried beneath a lacquer tree.]
就埋在漆树林落叶下
Seems you have quite the stroke of luck.
看来颜书吏运气颇佳
The murder weapon
这凶器
was discovered at the very last moment.
在最后一刻找到了
By checking the bow
以弓箭比对
and the calluses on their hands,
嫌犯手上的茧痕
I can identify the assassin.
下官就能确定谁是刺客
It appears I'm having a fortunate day.
看来本官今日运气不错
I arrived just in time.
来得正是时候
Lord Lai, your timing is impeccable.
来中丞来得这么及时
It must be more than just luck, right?
怕不只是因为运气吧
The murder weapon was transported from
凶器一路
Yan Gui Mountain to the Imperial Guard.
从雁归山送至内卫府
The news must have
消息必定
already reached the Imperial Inspectorate.
早就传到御察司了
Six hours have passed.
三个时辰到了
Clerk Yan, you need to hurry.
颜书吏抓紧吧
I'm very eager to see
本官很想看看
who had the audacity
是哪一位胆大包天
to make attempts on my life.
要杀了本官
You two,
两位
please
请你们
hold the bow
以平日握弓的方式
as you normally would.
握一下弓箭
I've figured out who the assassin is.
我想我知道刺客是谁了
The calluses on their hands
两位嫌犯握弓的茧痕
are nearly identical,
几乎一样
but the calluses from holding the bow
但架箭所致的茧痕
are distinctly different.
却有所不同
One of them has
一位
calluses on the inner side of his thumb,
是拇指内侧有茧子
indicating he uses the
说明他是用
inner side of his thumb to hold the bow.
拇指内侧架箭
This method of holding the bow
这种持弓方式
is known to those skilled in archery
擅用箭的都知道
as a low push with a slanted grip,
为斜持低推
which compromises the accuracy.
射箭精度不足
The other suspect
而另一位
has calluses on the web of his thumb,
是虎口处有茧子
indicating he uses a high push grip, which
为正持高推
is advantageous for precise shooting.
利于精准射击
Therefore,
故
the assassin is you.
刺客就是你
Don't move! Everyone, stay still!
别动 都别动
Step back! Step back!
退后 退后
Don't come any closer!
不要靠近我
Let me go!
放我走
Or I'll kill her!
不然我杀死她
Do you even realize where you are at?
也不看看这是什么地方
Do you really believe you can escape?
你以为你能逃得脱吗
Tell me who is behind this,
说出幕后指使之人
and I might spare your life.
我还能饶你个全尸
You better release her!
还不快放人
Since we have both the suspect and
既然人赃俱获
the evidence, we don't need a confession.
口供不要也罢
Prepare to execute.
准备射杀
You!
你
Are you going to shoot her as well?
你要连她一起射死吗
She's not even part of my Imperial Guard.
她又不是我内卫府的人
She's a mere clerk
一个连品阶都没有的
with no official rank.
小书吏
Losing her
少一个也没有
won't matter.
什么大不了的
Shen Du,
沈渡
you heartless White Death!
你这个黑心的白无常
How can you be so ruthless?
怎么能如此草菅人命呢
If you go down with the assassin,
你若是与嫌犯同去
I will deem you a hero of the empire.
我算你为国尽忠
As far as I know,
据我所知
the salary of a clerk is meager,
书吏的俸禄微薄
but the Ministry of Justice provides the
但刑部一向都是六部中
highest compensation among all ministries.
抚恤金给得最高的
Your parents didn't raise you for nothing.
你父母也算是没白养你
Even if I become a ghost,
我就算做鬼
I'll come back and haunt you!
也不会放过你的
Good.
巧了
The least I fear in my life
我沈某这辈子最不怕的
is a haunting ghost.
就是索命恶鬼了
Don't move! Everyone, stay still!
别动 都别动
Thank you.
多谢
That's not half bad.
还不算笨
[There's no way out,]
既然没有活路
fine!
那好
Tell me,
说
who sent you to kill me?
是谁派你来杀我的
It's...
是
It's him!
是他
Commander Shen, no wonder
沈大阁领
you were so eager to silence him.
怪不得一直急着灭口
Impressive!
厉害啊
Lord Lai,
来中丞
you believe the last words
恶犯临死前的
of a dying criminal?
一派胡言你也信
Isn't that ridiculous?
岂不让人笑话
Who do you think you are,
你算什么东西
to speak to Lord Lai like that?
敢跟我们中丞这么讲话
Lord Lai, I urge you to reconsider.
来中丞请三思
If it really was the commander,
若真是大阁领指派杀手
the Imperial Guard
内卫府
wouldn't have bothered to make arrests
何苦又是抓人
and search for evidence.
又是找凶器
They could have silenced him early on.
一早灭口不就好了
I was just joking.
来某玩笑而已
How could I possibly believe it was you?
怎么可能信你要杀我呢
Don't take it seriously.
不要当真啊
I
沈某
never took it seriously.
从未当真
The murderer has been brought to justice.
凶手既已伏法
I'm at ease then.
来某便放心了
There's no need for me to linger in here.
也不便在内卫府逗留
I'll take my leave now.
告辞
We failed our duties to watch over
属下看守嫌犯失职
the suspect; please punish us.
请大阁领责罚
The assassin is dead. Forget about it.
人死了就算了
You all,
你们几个
escort clerk Yan
把颜书吏
and the others
还有其余闲杂人等
out of here.
送出去吧
Yes, my lord.
是
My Lord,
大阁领
I noticed that little girl
我发现刚刚那个小书吏
was staring at you.
一直盯着您看
She doesn't seem to be afraid of you.
她居然不怕您
What's so surprising about that?
有什么好稀奇的
In this Xiang'an city,
这襄安城里
aren't there plenty of idle women?
无聊的女子还少吗
That's true.
也是
Your looks
您的容貌
could indeed attract some
还是能吸引到一些
reckless and horny women.
好色又不要命的女子
One more word, I'll
再敢废话
reassign you to Imperial Inspectorate.
送你去御察司任职
Please don't!
别呀
I just want to work for the Imperial Guard
景林就想在内卫府
for a lifetime.
干一辈子
Oh, I see.
我知道了
The Lady Yan (third eldest daughter) you are to marry
您要娶的颜三娘
is from the Yan Family.
就是颜博士府的
This girl (six eldest daughter)
这颜六娘
is your sister-in-law!
她是您的妻妹啊
She seems to
她看起来
be quite smart,
还算是有点脑子
understanding that I was trying
知道本阁领这么做
to save her.
是为了救她
As for being my sister-in-law...
至于妻妹嘛
That depends on whether her sister
那要看她那位三姐
has the courage
有没有胆子
to marry me, Shen Du.
嫁给我沈渡为妻了
What the...
这
Gratitude, lady Yan!
多谢颜书吏舍命相救
Please, get up.
快快请起
As a staff of the Ministry of Justice,
我在刑部当差
this is simply part of my duty.
这本就是我分内之事
[If it weren't for your sharp insights,]
要不是颜书吏断案如神
[we might not have made it alive]
我们就没命回去
[to reunite with our families again.]
见家人了
It's getting late.
天色已晚
You should all head home.
诸位还是赶快回家吧
Thank you once again, lady Yan.
多谢颜书吏
Let's go.
走
Lady.
姐姐
Your amazing skills are a marvel to behold.
今日一睹姐姐破案风采
You are truly resourceful, and
姐姐足智多谋
you didn't hesitate to face danger,
还临难不避
saving my life.
救了野云的命
Come on.
来
I wish to become your disciple.
所以野云想拜姐姐为师
Don't reject me please.
还请姐姐不要拒绝
I'm just a
我还是一个
lowly clerk with no official rank.
没有品阶的小书吏呢
How could I possibly take on a disciple?
如何能收徒呢
Besides,
再者
your parents
你的父母亲
would never allow you
也不会允许
to take a woman as your master.
你拜一个女子为师的
I am an orphan.
我无父无母
I was raised in the village of
是吃雁归山村
Yan Gui Mountain by the villagers.
百家饭长大
If I choose a master,
我认准的师父
I'm determined to become her disciple.
拜就是了
But you are not
可你不是
the disciple she chooses,
她认准的徒弟啊
young man.
小弟弟
Lady.
姐姐
Is that what you thought?
你当真这么想
Get in, Xing.
上车吧 六娘
So long.
走了
Yeah,
对了
how did you know that
你怎么知道
I was at the Imperial Guard?
我在内卫府啊
It was the worker from
是我家铺子的那个
my family's shop
包打听的小伙计
who informed me.
告诉我的
He mentioned that
他说
his cousin's classmate's
他表兄的同窗的
female cousin's sister-in-law
堂妹的表嫂
saw several villagers
在雁归山村
and a female clerk
看见有几个村民
from the Ministry of Justice
和刑部女书吏
being taken to the Imperial Guard.
一起被抓到了内卫府
A female clerk from
刑部书吏
the Ministry of Justice,
还是个女的
who else could it be but you?
除了你还有谁
So it seems that
那看来
worker from your family is better suited
你们家那个小伙计
for the Ministry of Justice than you are.
比你适合待在刑部
At first, when I heard the news,
原本我一听
I was really worried.
都急得不得了了
But then I found out
还好我一听
you were there to investigate a case,
你是去查案的
and I felt
那我就放
completely at ease.
一百八十个心了
In this world,
这世上
is there any case
还有你颜六娘
that you, Yan Xing, couldn't solve?
破不了的案吗
Besides,
而且
you have connections
这内卫府
at the Imperial Guard, don't you?
你不是还有熟人吗
No way!
不是吧
That Shen Du
那个沈渡
hasn't recognized you yet?
还没有认出你来
Is he blind or what?
他莫不是瞎了吧
Never mind.
那个算了
I think I should take you home first.
我看我先送你回家吧
I'm not going home.
我不回家
Drop me off at the Ministry of Justice.
你把我送到刑部就行
The Ministry of Justice?
刑部
Yan Xing!
颜六娘
I'm signing up for the female official exam tomorrow.
明日可是女官考核报名
All the women
人家襄安城里的女子
in Xiang'an City
一个个
are eager to become
都想着像你三姐一样
renowned ladies
成为远近闻名
like your third sister.
才望高雅的大家闺秀
I guess you are the only girl who's eager
一心只想考女官的
to become a female official.
估计也只有你了
You've already become a female official,
你都已经是女官了
so I can't fall behind!
那我可不能太落后啊
Don't worry.
你放心吧
This year I'll definitely become a proper
我今年一定能成为
female official at the Ministry of Justice.
堂堂正正的刑部女官
Turn right up ahead
前面右拐
to the Ministry of Justice.
去刑部
My Lord,
相爷
the assassin have committed suicide.
派去的死士已当场自尽
In this case,
如此一来
the competition between those two
这二虎相争
is going to be even more amusing.
可就更有看头了
Did you find out what the
国师在临死前的
prophecy was
那个预言
before the Royal Advisor died?
查出说的是什么了吗
It is said that the prophecy
据说
mentions the phoenix leading nine chicks
预言除了凤引九雏
and peace in the world,
天下太平之外
and there's a second half.
还有下半句
But no one knows what it is.
可谁都说不上来是什么
It seems no one knows.
似乎无人知晓
On the night he passed away,
国师逝世的当晚
the White Death and Dark Demon
这白无常和黑罗刹
were both present in the Ming Hall.
可都在明堂
Those two
这两个
mysterious men are quite something.
人鬼莫测的家伙呀
What's going on?
出什么事了
I am Yan Xing.
我是颜家六娘
Let me in!
让我进去
[In accordance with heaven's will,]
应天顺时
[I receive this clear order.]
受兹明命
[The Yan Family has a daughter,]
颜氏有女
[with remarkable poetic talent.]
咏絮之才
[She excels in both writing and painting,]
笔歌墨舞
[depicting phoenixes and dragons.]
描鸾刺凤
[She is well-versed in classics,]
经明行修
[knowledgeable in ancient and modern times.]
博古通今
[Her reputation as a virtuous lady]
其贤德淑女之名
- [is unmatched in Xiang'an.] - Mother.
冠绝襄安 阿娘
[I have heard of her with great delight.]
吾躬闻之甚悦
[The CO of the Imperial Guard, Shen Du,]
今内卫府大阁领沈渡
[is of marriageable age.]
适婚娶之时
[He should pick a virtuous lady as his wife.]
当择贤女与配
[The Yan Family has a daughter,]
值颜家女待字闺中
[perfectly matched with Shen Du.]
与沈渡天造地设
[To fulfill this union,]
为成人之美
[I grant them]
特赐二人
[to marry in three days.]
于三日后成婚
[I hereby decree.]
钦
Erudite Yan.
颜博士
Receive the decree.
接旨吧
[Shen Du?]
沈渡
My gratitude, Your Highness!
谢太皇太后圣恩
Thank you, my lord.
有劳公公了
Congratulations, Erudite Yan,
恭祝颜博士
for raising a daughter like Caiwei,
培养了像三姑娘这样
who is renowned for her talent and virtue.
名动襄安的才德淑女
My Caiwei!
我的采薇啊
She can't get married!
采薇不能嫁
Regarding a daughter's marriage,
这女儿家的婚事
it has to be the parents' decision
向来是父母之命
and the matchmaker's words.
媒妁之言
Moreover, this is a marriage
更何况
granted by the Empress Dowager herself.
这是太皇太后金口赐婚
That's the White Death!
那可是白无常呀
If our Caiwei marries him,
咱们家采薇嫁过去
then
这
she will definitely suffer!
还能有好日子过吗
Things are unpredictable.
世事无常啊
I never expected this, not at all.
想不到 完全想不到
It's tragic.
凄惨
Mother,
娘
why are you staring at me?
你总盯着我干吗
People say
人家说
great wisdom appears foolish.
大智若愚
Could it be talking about you?
你莫不就是大智若愚吧
I always feel that I have
娘总觉得自己
no talents or renowned social status.
没能力没地位
You were born as a concubine's daughter,
生下个你就是个庶女
not being valued.
不受人待见
So I always want you
所以总想让你
to learn from Caiwei,
好好学学你三姐
to behave like a proper lady,
习个淑女的样子
and find a good husband,
将来找个好人家
to secure a good path for your future.
为后半生谋个好出路
Mother,
阿娘
you know I don't like those things.
你知道我不喜欢那些
Yes,
是啊
I used to get angry,
我以前也总生气
blaming you for being foolish,
总怪你蠢笨
uneducated.
不学无术
But now,
可如今
I suddenly feel
我竟突然觉得
that being uneducated is actually good.
不学无术挺好
Being uneducated
不学无术啊
can actually be quite nice.
真的挺好
Mother, I am not uneducated.
阿娘 我没有不学无术
Just think about it,
你想啊
with so many women in all of Xiang'an,
全襄安城那么多的女子
why is it that Caiwei
怎么就偏偏你三姐
was chosen by the Empress Dowager?
被太皇太后给看上了
It's because
那就是因为
her talent is truly exceptional.
她的才华太出众了
Her mom has nurtured her since childhood
大夫人从小培养她
in music, chess, calligraphy, and painting,
琴棋书画 诗词歌赋
and she excels in all of them.
那是样样精通
But who would have thought that now
可没想到现如今
she would marry the White Death,
居然嫁给了白无常
jumping into his underworld?
要跳进他的阎王殿
Mother,
阿娘
Shen Du is the
人家沈渡
commander of the Imperial Guard.
是内卫府的大阁领
He's not as unworthy as you think.
没有你说的那么不堪
Do you think
那你以为
Caiwei and her mother
大夫人和你三姐
were just putting on a show by crying?
一哭二闹的是在做戏呢
In any case,
总之
even if Caiwei has the fate to marry him,
你三姐就算有命嫁过去
she will be tormented to the point of
也会活活地被折磨至
wishing...
生
she
生不如
were dead.
生不如死